Room E.01 Helmholtzstr. 18 89081 Ulm, Germany

Lukas Niebel

PhD Student at Ulm University

+49 157 83632890 lukasniebel.github.io niebel.math@gmail.com

I am a PhD student at Ulm University under the supervision of Prof. Rico Zacher. My research concerns the regularity theory of linear and nonlinear kinetic partial differential equations. I am interested in a precise L^p -solution theory for linear kinetic PDE and in understanding a priori estimates for weak solutions of kinetic PDE. The goal is to apply these results to nonlinear kinetic partial differential equations such as the Boltzmann and Landau equations. Preprints of all publications are available on arXiv.

PUBLICATIONS

Kinetic maximal L^p -regularity with temporal weights and application to quasilinear kinetic diffusion equations	2022
with Rico Zacher, Journal of Differential Equations, 307, p. 29–82, link to the article.	
Kinetic maximal $L^p_u(L^p)$ -regularity for the fractional Kolmogorov equation with variable density	2022
Nonlinear Analysis, 214, link to the article.	
Kinetic maximal L^2 -regularity for the (fractional) Kolmogorov equation	2021
with Rico Zacher, Journal of Evolution Equations, 21, p. 3585–3612, link to the article.	

EDUCATION

PhD student 2019 - 2022

Ulm University

- Working title: Analytic aspects of kinetic partial differential equations
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Rico Zacher
- My studies are funded by a graduate scholarship (grant number 1902 LGFG-E).

M.Sc. Mathematics 2018 - 2019

Ulm University

- Thesis: Kolmogorov equations Well-posedness, regularity, asymptotics and Harnack inequalities
- Grade: 1.0 with distinction, awarded for best graduation
- During my master's studies, I focused on Analysis, by taking courses on the calculus of variations, evolution equations, functional calculus, partial differential equations and optimal transport. This was supported by courses in applied mathematics, such as numerical finance, as well as a series of lectures on econophysics.

B.Sc. Mathematics 2014 - 2018

Ulm University

- Thesis: Long-time behavior of Markov chains by discrete functional inequalities and entropic Ricci curvature
- Grade: 1.1 with distinction, awarded for best graduation

Abitur, Joachim-Hahn-Gymnasium Blaubeuren 2014 2013 - 2014

Junior studies in mathematics, Fernuniversität Hagen and PfH Göttingen

WORKING AND TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Scientific assistant 2020 - 2022

University of Applied Sciences Neu-Ulm (HNU)

Neu-Ulm, Germany

 Design and supervision of a supplementary course on statistics and applications for first-year students with an emphasis on programming in R.

Working student 2015 - 2019

Daimler AG Research & Development

Ulm, Germany

- Statistical Analysis with Matlab and Excel.
- Supervising the operation of a quasi-static tension-compression testing machine.

Scientific assistant 2017 - 2019Ulm University Ulm, Germany

- Head of teaching assistants for Analysis 1, Analysis 2, Dynamical Systems, Elements of Functional analysis; Creation and presentation of exercises supplementary to the lectures, responsible for the student assistants.
- Organisation of the Trainingscamp, a yearly event for first-year students to refresh their mathematical skills.

Student assistant 2015 - 2017Ulm University Ulm, Germany

• Tutor for the Mathlab Analysis 1 and Analysis 2.

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

AWARDS AND SCHOLAR	SHIPS	
Master graduation award 'Graduate scholarship gran Bachelor graduation awar	inU Mobility-Programm, Ulm University (1000 €) "Absolventenpreis M.Sc. Mathematik Uni Ulm 2020" for the best graduation nted by the State of Baden-Wuerttemberg, Germany (grant number 1902 LGFG-E) d "Absolventenpreis B.Sc. Mathematik Uni Ulm 2018" for the best graduation graduation award of the "Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft"	2022 2022 2019 — 2022 2018 2014
VOLUNTEER WORK		
Representing the interest the PhD regulations. Sin Elected member of the fac Member of the Academic S	uncil of PhD students at Ulm University sts of doctoral students in university committees, e.g. for the change of nce 12/2021, chair of the PhD council. culty council for Mathematics and Economic Sciences of Ulm University Student Council Mathematics ointment committee for a professorship in "Stochastics"	2020 — 2022 2020 — 2022 2017 — 2019
OTHER SCIENTIFIC ACTI	VITIES	
Series of talks (five per t	ninar "Mathematisches Kolloquium" at Ulm University erm) at which researchers are invited to give a talk accessible to a broad audience	2020 — 2022
9	rkshop for PhD students in mathematics at Ulm University	2022
	ipants, Funding (approx. 2000 €) acquired by the Proko Ulm University or the workshop of the 25th Internetseminar	2022
	tion in $L^p(\mathbb{R}^{2n})$ – Semigroup, spectrum, maximal regularity?	2022
Research stay at Prof. Dr. (Cyril Imbert, École normale supérieure Paris, one week	2021
Facilitator at the autumn s	school "COLLAB – Collaboratory for Global Sustainability 2021"	2021
TALKS AND POSTERS		
	hool on "Methods and Models of Kinetic Theory", Pesaro	2022
-	ysis of kinetic equations, INI Cambridge	2022 2021
Talk — Norilliear Evolution Talk — Oberseminar Analy	n Equations and Approximations, Essen	2021
	Analysis and Applied Mathematics, Münster	2021
ATTENDED CONFERENC	ES	
25th Internetseminar "Spe	ectral Theory for Operators and Semigroups", Agropoli	2022
	Methods and Models of Kinetic Theory", Pesaro	2022
Oxbridge PDE Conference,		2022
	Between Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh ew tutorial, INI Cambridge (virtual)	2022 2022
-	etic equations, INI Cambridge (virtual)	2022
	differential equations, INI Cambridge (virtual)	2021
	ent Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna (virtual)	2021
	odeling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille (virtual)	2021
	and Applied Mathematics, Münster (virtual)	2021
	ons: Particle Systems, Hyperbolic Conservation Laws, CIRM Marseille	2019
	ions, Harmonic Analysis And Spectral Theory, Bad Herrenalb	2019
Non Standard Diffusions in Evolution Equations in Ulr	n Fluids, Kinetic Equations and Probability, CIRM Marseille m, Ulm	2018 2018
SKILLS		
Communication IT Skills	German (native speaker), English (C1), French (B1) C++, Excel (VBA), Java, ŁTĘX, Mathematica, Matlab, R, Swift	

C++, Excel (VBA), Java, ŁTŁX, Mathematica, Matlab, R, Swift Advanced understanding of software and hardware